只有一种生物为了自己的生存
Only one creature has carved a life for itself
在地球的每一个角落留下了印迹
in every habitat on Earth.
那就是人类
That creature is us.
天地悠悠
All over the world we still
我们仍依靠创造力来努力存活于世
use our ingenuity to survive in the wild places,
远离文明开化的城市
far from the city lights,
直面原始险恶的自然
face to face with raw nature.
绵延的山脉是地球上最为恶劣的环境之一
Mountains are among the most brutal environments on earth.
天气可以在数小时之内由酷热变为极寒
Weather here can shift from tropical to arctic in just hours.
海拔越高的地方  环境越为恶劣
And the higher you climb, the tougher it gets,
直到连氧气都消失殆尽
until even oxygen is stripped away.
然而  数百万人口居住于此
But millions of people live in the mountains,
或在困境中求得一席之地
either seeking refuge from conflict
或开发特有资源
or exploiting resources found nowhere else.
因此  他们不得不采用
And to survive they have had to adapt
令人惊叹并充满智慧的生存方式
in the most surprising and ingenious ways.
这就是他们的故事
These are their stories.
山区
空气稀薄之地的生活
阿尔泰山位于蒙古境内
The Altai mountains in mongolia
是世界上最为偏僻的地区之一
are among the most remote on earth.
对于生活在这个贫瘠之地的人们来说
And for the people who live in this barren landscape,
捕猎几乎是不可能的
hunting is nearly impossible.
除非你有帮手
Unless you have help.
塞劳・扎迪克和他儿子贝瑞克是哈萨克族人
Sailau Jadik and his son Berik are Kazakhs.
今天他们要寻找一个最佳捕猎搭档
And today they're in search of the ultimate hunting partner.
一只金鹰
A golden eagle.
有一只鹰当搭档的话...
就可以捕捉到任何猎物
它是地球上的最佳猎手
小鹰们已为离巢做好准备
These young birds are almost ready to leave the nest.
如果十六岁的贝瑞克能抓到一只小鹰
If 16-year-old Berik can collect one,
在成为他父亲那样的哈萨克猎手之路上
he will take his first step towards becoming a Kazakh hunter
就迈出了第一步
like his father.
这可是意义非凡的第一步
It's a big first step.
小心点
别踩到小鹰
自从大约二百年前
Ever since the Kazakhs fled
哈萨克族人逃到这片山区以来
into these mountains nearly 200 years ago,
他们就一直在窃取雏鹰
they have been stealing baby eagles.
鹰的视力比人类的强很多
Eagles have eyes many times more powerful than a human's
能看到两公里以内的猎物
and can spot prey two kilometres away.
贝瑞克如果能驯化这只鹰为他捕猎
If Berik can teach this eagle to hunt for him,
他就能加入哈萨克族为数不多的猎手行列
he will join the few hundred Kazakhs left who can still do this.
干得好贝瑞克  这只鹰非常好
贝瑞克给这只小鹰取名为巴拉潘
Berik calls his new eagle Balapan.
如果训练得好  巴拉潘会成为他的捕猎搭档
If he gets it right, Balapan will become his hunting partner.
但是要训练上五个月
But training her will take five months.
五个月后
It's five months later,
是贝瑞克和羽翼丰满的巴拉潘
and time for Berik and a fully grown Balapan
一起去首次捕猎的时候了
to go on their first hunt together.
他们正在追赶一直蒙古狐狸
They're after a Mongolian fox,
这种动物难以追捕
an animal so elusive,
只有老鹰有机会抓住它
only an eagle stands a chance of catching it.
为了让巴拉潘捕捉到这只狐狸
But for Balapan to catch the fox,
贝瑞克首先要把她带到高地
Berik first has to take her to high ground.
在这里  她有一个最佳的视角
Here she'll have the perfect
任何细微的移动都无法从她眼中逃脱
vantage point to spot the slightest movement.
仔细看  我觉得狐狸藏在那边
在那些岩石里面
听我的指示  让鹰做好准备
当她看见鹰的时候  立刻放开她
贝瑞克希望巴拉潘的猎捕本能发挥作用
Berik now hopes that Balapan's hunting instinct will take over.
准备
巴拉潘失败了
Balapan has failed.
对于贝瑞克而言  这让他担忧
For Berik, this is worrying.
她有没有当猎手的潜质呢
Does she have the killer instinct?
一般来讲  哈萨克族猎手
Traditionally, Kazakh hunters
和他们的鹰会朝夕相处长达七年
pair up with their eagles for seven years
然后让它们回归自然
before setting them free,
但此刻贝瑞克产生了怀疑
but Berik now has his doubts.
不要担心
她从未见过那样跳跃的狐狸
明天就会成功的
破晓时分  父子二人再次来到了这个山头
As day breaks, father and son return to the mountains.
如果巴拉潘抓不到狐狸
If Balapan can't catch a fox,
贝瑞克只能将她放走  再找一只鹰来训练
Berik may have to let her go and find another eagle to train.
巴拉潘抓到了狐狸  就如平时训练的那样
Balapan has caught the fox, just as she was trained to.
现在她要奋力困住狐狸
She's now locked in a fight to the death.
塞劳以最快的速度杀死狐狸
Sailau kills the fox as quickly as he can.
按照哈萨克族的传统
According to Kazakh tradition,
巴拉潘可以食用狐狸的内脏
Balapan gets the fox's lungs.
狐狸的皮毛可以用来做冬衣
The fox's thick coat will be used for winter clothing.
贝瑞克证明了自己是名优秀的哈萨克猎人
Berik has proved himself to be a successful Kazakh hunter.
恭喜你  我的儿子
我为你骄傲
你现在是一个真正的哈萨克人了
只要哈萨克人居住在阿尔泰山地区
As long as they have lived in the Altai Mountains,
他们就要依靠鹰来生活
Kazakhs have relied on eagles.
然而  不是所有山区人民
However, not all mountain people
都要依靠野生动物生活的
get help from wild animals.
在东非大裂谷边缘地带
On the edge of Africa's Great Rift Valley,
地质变动造就了埃塞俄比亚瑟门山脉
geological upheaval has created Ethiopia's Simien mountains.
在这里  巨大的悬崖形成了一个天然屏障
Here, giant cliffs form a natural fortress
为这里受战争影响几个世纪的人们
where for centuries people
提供了一个庇护所
have sought refuge from conflicts below.
盖比村是上百个位于
Getabit village is one of
高地的村庄中的一个
a hundred perched in a landscape so vertical
村民们只能在
that the residents can
悬崖边缘的小块土地上
only grow their crops on tiny strips of land
种些农作物
along the edges of cliffs.
七百英尺高的悬崖并不是他们最担心的事
But 700-foot precipices are the least of their worries.
今天正是每年的丰收时节
Today their annual harvest is under way,
他们要保护粮食远离敌人贪婪的魔掌
and their grain is under attack from a ravenous enemy.
敌人就是狮尾狒狒
These are gelada monkeys
他们喜偷农民的粮食
and they love stealing the farmers' grain.
六百多只狒狒潜伏在盖比村附近
Troops of up to 600 prowl the cliffs surrounding Getabit village,
由雄性狒狒带领  其獠牙长于狮子
led by males with fangs larger than a lion's.
他们是狡猾的窃贼
They are cunning thieves.
为了抵御狒狒的攻击
To defend their crops against the monkeys,
农民们让孩子来保护粮食
the cliff farmers depend on their children,
比如  这个十二岁的德杰
such as 12-year-old Dereje.
狒狒的力气很大
它们杀死过很多羊
很多人都被它们伤过
滚开
我非常讨厌它们
由于这里靠近国家公园
Because the area is next to a national park,
所以狮尾狒狒是受保护的
the gelada are protected.
滚开
杀一只狒狒就要坐七年牢
所以只能吓跑它们
夜幕降临  狒狒停止进攻
As night approaches, the geladas stop raiding.
而德杰家的粮食正在等待收割
But Dereje's crops are ripe for harvest,
他明白
and he knows that tomorrow
明天狒狒的攻击会比以往更加激烈
the monkeys will attack even more aggressively than before.
所以他和兄妹们在地里守夜
So, with his two sisters and brother, he camps by his fields.
它们今天吃了很多粮食
如果它们来一大群怎么办呢
大的我来搞定
你必须勇敢面对
赶走它
晚上  气温骤降到零下
At night, temperatures plummet below freezing.
虽然有着厚厚皮毛的狒狒适应这样的温度
While the thick-furred geladas have adapted to the cold,
但人类不得不抱作一团相互取暖
the humans must huddle together for warmth.
黎明时刻  狒狒来袭
At dawn, the geladas attack.
第一次进攻有几只大的雄性狒狒
The first strike comes from a few large males,
目标就是德杰看守的干草堆
who target Dereje's haystacks.
德杰赶走了它们
He drives them off,
但狒狒是如此狡猾
but the geladas are cunning
这几只只是声东击西的诱饵
these males were only a decoy.
德杰家土地的另一边在视野之外
Out of sight at the other end of Dereje's fields,
大部队来临  一场真正的掠夺开始了
the main army launches the real attack.
这么多的狒狒几分钟就能将作物消灭干净
A big troop like this can strip a field in minutes.
看着点  狒狒正在偷吃
它们在庄稼地里
从哪边来的
在另一边偷吃粮食
德杰要迅速赶到
If Dereje doesn't hurry,
否则他家过冬的粮食就没了
the food his family needs to get through the winter will be gone.
德杰成功了  他赶走了狒狒
Dereje's done it. He's seen off the gelada.
终于  他们满载而归
Finally, his crops are harvested.
粮食安全了  我很高兴
现在能在家里睡觉了
德杰生活在瑟门山区
Dereje lives in the Simiens
是因为几百年前他的祖先逃难于此
because his ancestors sought refuge here centuries ago.
然而  在世界的某些角落  人们定居山区
But in some parts of the world, people settle in mountains
是因为这里有他们极为想得到的东西
because this environment has something they desperately want.
大陆板块的撞击诞生了山脉
Mountains are born when continental plates collide.
这种地质巨变
This massive upheaval
通常会迸发出丰富而珍贵的矿物质
often exposes a wealth of valuable minerals.
尤以印度尼西亚而闻名
Nowhere more so than here in Indonesia,
这是地球上活火山最多的国家
home to more active volcanic mountains than any nation on Earth.
在这里  人们冒着生命危险
Here, people risk their lives
开采一种很多重要工业都需要的矿物质
for a mineral vital to several important industries.
那就是硫磺
Sulphur.
哈图姆和苏莱曼是硫磺的开采者
Hartomo and Sulaiman are sulphur miners.
今天  他们要前往极少数人才敢去的地方
Today, they're going where few others dare.
进入一座活火山的腹地
Into the heart of an active volcano.
这里有很多高山  但是只有一座有硫磺
这里是夷真火山口  地球上毒性最强的地方
This is Ijen crater, one of the most poisonous places on Earth.
在其中心  湖水中充满了
At its centre, a lake filled with
二百五十万吨的酸
two-and-a-half million tonnes of acid.
散发到山外的的有毒气体
And out of the depths of the mountain pour toxic gases
在过去四十年中已经令七十四名矿工丧命
that have claimed the lives of 74 miners in the past 40 years.
火山所散发的气体很危险
这能令人昏死过去
每当我们来这里  家人就会担心
这些矿工吸进的硫化氢
The hydrogen sulphide that these men must breathe in
是安全限度的四十倍
is 40 times the safe level.
久而久之  他们的肺部会受到损害
Over time, it destroys their lungs.
这气体很熏眼睛...
而且会伤到喉咙和肺部
当他们采到足够的硫磺
Once they have enough sulphur,
哈图姆和苏莱曼就将这些东西
Hartomo and Sulaiman have to carry it
直接运到二百米外的火山口边缘地带
200 metres straight up to the crater rim.
每个人负重九十公斤
Each man hefts 90 kilos,
几乎是正常负重的一倍半
nearly one-and-a-half times their own body weight.
这种工作在矿工的身体上留下沉重的代价
This work exacts a heavy price on the miners' bodies.
他们说在这里工作会缩短寿命
我为了养活妻儿不得如此
别的工作都不如这个挣得多
苏莱曼和哈图姆每次能获得五美元
Sulaiman and Hartomo are paid five dollars per load.
矿工们的生活通常很艰苦
The lives of miners have always been hard.
但这艰苦的生活并不仅限于矿工
But it's not just miners who have it tough.
一些山区的居民  寻找食物甚至成为问题
For some mountain dwellers, just finding food can be a challenge.
我们来到位于南太平洋的
In the South Pacific lies
世界第二大岛  新几内亚岛
the world's second largest island, New Guinea.
从生物学角度来讲  这是地球上
This is one of the most
最为富饶的山区之一
biologically rich mountain landscapes on Earth.
这里丰富的水资源和森林保护区
With plenty of water, and thousands of protected valleys,
孕育着这里的生命
these mountains brim with life.
但是  猎取食物却十分困难
Yet hunting for food, and particularly meat,
尤其是肉质食物
is surprisingly difficult.
马库斯  安德鲁和乔治是
Marcus, Andrew and George are hunters
央格鲁博肯族的猎手
from the Yangoru Boiken tribe.
他们和家人
They and their families
已有两星期未吃到新鲜的肉食了
haven't eaten any fresh meat for two weeks.
今天  他们想改善一下伙食
But today they plan to solve the problem.
他们希望能够捕捉到狐蝠
They hope to trap giant fruit bats.
如果能抓到蝙蝠  家人们就有吃的了
孩子们常问我  爸爸  你能给我带些蝙蝠肉吗
捕获狐蝠需要做一个巨大的陷阱
But to catch a giant bat requires a giant bat trap.
这三人正在进行一项浩大的工程
So these men are doing something radical.
他们改造着这里的地貌
They're changing the shape of the landscape itself.
沿着山脊  开辟出宽七十英尺的门道
Along this ridge, the men create a 70-foot wide doorway.
一条小路通往远处的果树林
A shortcut through the mountains to the fruit trees beyond
这是捕捉蝙蝠的绝佳之地
and a perfect place to ambush the bats.
祖先们教我如何捕猎
教我如何设置陷阱和网
像蜘蛛一样  他们织了一张巨大的网
Like spiders, the men spin a gigantic web.
黑夜  蝙蝠是不会察觉到
In the dark, this 130-foot
这张一百三十英尺高的大网的
high net cannot be detected by the bats.
现在只剩两件事
Only two things now remain.
那就是  安置蝙蝠报警信号
Add the bat alert signal
和祈祷蝙蝠的到来
and pray the bats fly into their trap.
捕捉蝙蝠需要耐心
Catching bats requires patience.
以前  马库斯曾经在森林中等待数星期
In the past, Marcus has spent weeks on the mountain
却空手而归
and come home empty-handed.
但如果他能抓到几只蝙蝠
But if he does manage to catch even a few,
所作出的努力还是值得的
the effort will be worthwhile.
一只蝙蝠配上些大米
可以供给十二个人
有蝙蝠  有蝙蝠
在网里  快点儿
逃走前先杀了它
这只大的公蝙蝠够几个人吃的了
这是个好的开始  但是家中连月的口粮
It's a good start, but with all the mouths to feed at home,
需要更多的蝙蝠
they're going to need more than one bat.
时间一点点过去  他们继续捕捉蝙蝠
As the hours roll on, their trap continues to catch bats.
夜里  他们共捕到十五只蝙蝠
In the course of the night, the men catch a total of 15 bats.
现在煮熟了两只  余下的被保存起来
They cook two now and save the rest.
这些收获能够提供给家人们
Their haul will provide their families
两星期的蛋白质了
with enough protein for two weeks.
这肉的味道好极了
蝙蝠的每个部位都可以吃
Every part of the bat is edible,
甚至是翅膀上的皮
down to the leather on the wings.
对于安德鲁  马库斯和乔治来说
For Andrew, Marcus and George,
只有熟知他们所生活的每寸土地
knowing every inch of their mountain habitat
才能够养活家人
enables them to feed their families.
然而  严寒地带  熟知每寸土地
But in colder climes, knowing every inch of your mountain
却是生死一线的转机
can mean the difference between life and death.
在瑞士的阿尔卑斯山脉  全年降雪达十米厚
In the Swiss Alps, ten metres of snow can fall in a year.
对于几百万的滑雪爱好者来说
And for millions of skiers,
这是个圣地
this is a brilliant reason to come here.
但是暴雪也能构成生存威胁
But heavy snowfalls can also pose a deadly threat.
雪崩
Avalanches.
速度快于高速列车
Travelling faster than a bullet train,
雪崩所到之处  一切化为虚无
a major avalanche annihilates everything in its path.
过去的每个冬季
In any given winter,
仅在阿尔卑斯山脉就有三万场雪崩
there can be 30,000 avalanches in the Swiss Alps alone.
巡视员马丁・麦斯是一位雪崩观测员
Ski patrolman Martin Mathys is an avalanche spotter.
今天  他发现了一个问题
And today he has a big problem.
在他的家乡格林德瓦
In his hometown of Grindelwald,
已降雪多天
there has been a massive snowfall.
极有可能发生雪崩
The risk of avalanche is now extreme.
雪崩能毁灭汽车和火车
掩埋公路...
...和村庄
我的工作是在雪崩发生前将其制服
在格林德瓦之上  矗立着一千米高山峰
Towering 1,000 metres above Grindelwald
那便是耸人听闻的黑角山
is the notorious Black Horn ridge.
被积雪覆盖  马上就会爆发一场灾难
Packed with snow, it's a disaster waiting to happen.
在更多的积雪覆盖之前
So Martin must set off a controlled avalanche now
马丁必须立即采取措施
before any more snow falls.
紧急情况时  我们使用直升飞机
只有这样  才能安全地靠近
为了控制雪崩
To set off a controlled avalanche,
需要大量炸药
you need dynamite, plenty of it.
马丁带了五十公斤炸药  足够炸毁几个街区
Martin is taking 50 kilos, enough to blow up several city blocks.
这么多的雪令我的工作忙碌起来
我感到肾上腺素分泌
...但并不害怕
马丁到达黑角山的峰顶
Martin reaches the summit of the Black Horn ridge,
准备好炸药
and sets a charge.
他引发了一场微型雪崩  转移十多吨雪
He triggers a mini avalanche, shifting over ten tonnes of snow.
但这远远不够  他需要再次引发
But it's not enough. He needs to go again.
这一次  马丁成功了
This time, Martin succeeds.
这场人工雪崩令山区人民处于安全之中
This is the avalanche he needs to make the mountain safe.
大自然的力量非常强大...
雪崩是我们生活的一部分
我们时刻准备着
生活在阿尔卑斯山的人们已经学会
High in the Alps, mountain people have learnt
用现代科技对抗雪崩带来的威胁
to control the threat of avalanches with modern technology.
但是在另一些山区中
But there are mountains
大自然的力量是无法抗拒的
where the forces of nature cannot be tamed.
喜马拉雅山是地球最高山
The Himalaya is the highest mountain range on Earth.
数百座世界高峰均聚于此地
The world's tallest hundred mountains are all here.
在这些高峰之中  居住着七千万人
And within these peaks live 70 million people,
较高的海拔
many at altitudes that
对人体造成了伤害
pose a threat to the human body.
在尼泊尔的多兰巴地区
In the Doramba region of Nepal,
人们正面临不可见的威胁
the residents face an insidious threat.
危险的高强度紫外线
Dangerously high levels of
穿过稀薄的高山空气
harmful UV rays pierce the thin mountain air
会灼伤人们的眼睛
and burn people's eyes.
在这里的巴劳村
And here in the village of Balau,
六十五岁的特缇妮付出了沉重的代价
65-year-old Teteeni has paid a heavy price.
她已经瞎了
She's blind.
三年前  看东西开始模糊
后来我就彻底瞎了
但是哭并没有用
特缇妮决定
Teteeni is determined not
不能让失明妨碍到她的生活
to let blindness interfere with her life,
但是一些简单的工作
but simple tasks,
比如打水  就得花更多的时间
such as fetching water, now take longer
并且还很危险
and can be treacherous.
她的失明是由白内障引起的
Her blindness is caused by cataracts,
眼球内的晶状体
a fogging of her lenses exacerbated
由于高海拔处强烈的阳光照射而变得混浊
by the intense mountain sun.
此处位于喜马拉雅山脉  地处偏僻
But isolated here in the Himalaya,
特缇妮无法接受医学治疗
Teteeni has no access to medical treatment.
幸运的是  她心心念念的
Fortunately, an answer to
祷告即将得到回应
her prayers may be just around the corner.
加德满都[尼泊尔首都]的桑多克・鲁特医生
From Kathmandu, Dr. Sanduk Ruit
开创了一种新的眼部手术方法
has pioneered a method of eye surgery
并把这种技术带到喜马拉雅山偏远的村落
that he brings to the remote corners of the Himalaya.
他的流动诊所为成千上万人带来希望
His mobile clinic brings hope to thousands.
今天  特缇妮也要前往参与治疗
And today, Teteeni is setting off to join them.
在这山脉之间
She has arranged for the only transportation
她只能采用一种交通方式
available to her in these mountains.
一位朋友愿意背着她
A friend has offered to carry her
送她到十公里外的多兰巴诊所
ten kilometres to the Doramba clinic.
尽管鲁特医生的手术成功率很高
While Dr Ruit's success rate is high,
但特缇妮的眼睛仍可能
there is still a strong chance
因为失明太久而无法恢复
that Teteeni's eyes are too far gone to be saved.
他无法做出保证
He makes no promises.
多兰巴的学校
Doramba's schoolhouse
现在成为了临时手术室
is now an improvised operating theatre.
鲁特医生只用了半个小时
It takes Dr Ruit just half
就取出了特缇妮眼中混浊的晶状体
an hour to remove Teteeni's fogged lenses.
取而代之的是他自己制造的
He then replaces them
人工合成晶状体
with a synthetic lens he manufactures himself.
在西方国家
In the West,
这样一个手术要花费八千美元
this operation could cost 8,000 dollars.
不过有了慈善机构的资助
But, funded by charity,
鲁特医生不会收病人们一分钱
Dr Ruit doesn't charge his patients a single rupee.
手术结束后  特缇妮能做的只有等待
With surgery now complete, Teteeni can only wait.
二十四小时之后
Just 24 hours after her operation,
特缇妮和其他上百名病人一起
Teteeni joins hundreds of patients
等待着绷带被揭去的那一刻
waiting to have their bandages removed,
希望能重见天日
hopefully with her sight restored.
来看一下
对于特缇妮而言
For Teteeni,
这将是最关键的时刻
this is the moment of truth.
看着我
看这里
看得见吗
看得见  先生
告诉我你看见什么了
我看到你的鼻子还有嘴
我竖了几根手指
五根  先生
现在呢
两根
用你的手摸一下我鼻子
这里
是吗
再摸一下我的脸颊
轻轻的抚摸
-感觉怎么样  -非常好
这是三年来特缇妮第一次看清了世界
For the first time in three years, Teteeni can see.
愿上帝保佑鲁特医生
之前我什么也看不见  现在可以了
我的问题终于解决了
我的内心充满光明
在喜马拉雅山脚
In the Himalayan foothills,
现代医学正在帮助
modern medicine is helping prolong
这里的人们延长他们的寿命
the lives of the people who live here.
然而  当你攀越海拔越来越高时
But, as you climb higher in these mountains,
如何处理人类的死亡就成了一个难题
it's how to deal with death that poses a problem.
海拔四千多米之处
At over 4,000 metres,
多特拉是地球上最高部落之一
Dho Tarap is one of the highest communities on Earth.
这里的佛教徒几乎与世隔绝
Buddhists live here in almost complete isolation.
在这样的高海拔处  如果有人死亡
And when someone dies at this altitude,
处理尸体则是一个真正的挑战
dealing with the corpse is a real challenge.
昨天晚上  村里有人去世了
Last night, there was a death in the village.
七十岁的诺比拉刚刚过世
70-year-old Nombe-la passed away,
现在他的家人正在包裹尸体
and now his family are preparing his body
准备一场佛教葬礼
for a Buddhist funeral.
葬礼的主持人是神圣的朗杰喇嘛
The man in charge of this funeral is Holy Lama Namgyal.
诺比拉是一个很好的人
他工作勤奋...
教子有方
朗杰喇嘛必须马上举行葬礼
Lama Namgyal needs to hold the funeral soon
因为诺比拉的尸体
because Nombe-la's corpse
会引来食肉动物  还可能传播疾病
could attract predators and spread disease.
可是如果你生活在世界的屋脊
But when you live at the roof of the world,
选择就非常有限了
your options are limited.
佛教徒没有土葬
Buddhists don't bury their dead.
在这样的海拔下寸草不生
And at this altitude no trees grow,
因此也没有木料以供火葬
so there is no wood for a cremation.
唯一的办法是一种神圣的宗教仪式
The solution is a sacred ritual
比佛教本身更为悠久
older than Buddhism itself.
天葬
A sky burial.
天葬是这里的特殊习俗
为举行天葬
To conduct the sky burial ritual,
朗杰喇嘛需要专业人员的协助
Lama Namgyal needs the help of a specialist.
巴尔玛・福巴是送葬人
Bharmay Furba is the undertaker.
作为非佛教徒  他是唯一一名
As a non-Buddhist, he is the only one
可以执行这项艰难任务的人
who is allowed to carry out this most difficult task.
喇嘛没法做我的工作
我参与过很多次天葬
但仍需要喝些酒
送葬的队伍
The funeral procession
要行进一个半小时
heads an hour-and-a-half up into the mountains
才能到达山里举行天葬的神台
to a sacred ledge where sky burials have been performed
在那里  天葬已有一千多年的历史
for over 1,000 years.
他们将与这崇山之中
Here, they will rendezvous
最为高效的食腐动物会合
with the most efficient scavengers in these mountains.
秃鹫
Vultures.
数千年来
For millennia,
这里的佛教徒们就是依靠
Buddhists in these mountains
山里的秃鹫和髭兀鹰
have relied on the griffon vulture
来帮助他们处理尸体的
and the lammergeier to help them dispose of their dead.
这些鸟类可以在疾病传播之前
These birds swiftly consume
迅速消灭掉尸体
a corpse before it can spread disease.
佛教徒们认为这样的行为非常神圣
Buddhists see this as a sacred act,
是赐予他们的恩惠
an offering that will sustain
让他们以另一种方式延续生命
the life of another being.
对他们而言
For them,
诺比拉的尸体现在就是一个空容器
Nombe-la's corpse is now an empty vessel.
他的灵魂已经去了另一国度
His soul has already migrated to another realm.
诺比拉的儿子们最后一次向父亲行礼
Nombe-la's sons pay their final respects to their father.
但他们不愿意
But they don't wish to
目睹接下来即将发生的事
be present for what is about to take place.
为了让秃鹫尽快
Because in order for the vultures
处理诺比拉的尸体
to consume Nombe-la's corpse quickly,
巴尔玛必须为它们提供方便
Bharmay must make it easier for them.
诺比拉的尸体现在已被消耗殆尽
Nombe-la's corpse is now gone
不会再传播疾病了
and cannot spread disease.
山上所有的生命...
都是相互依存的
诺比拉的血肉为秃鹫提供了食物
这是善业
为了在高山间生活下去
To survive in the mountains,
你必须理解他们
you have to understand them.
山野间的生活环境十分残酷
Mountain habitats can be brutal
但是只要动用聪明才智和果敢的决断力
but if you use your ingenuity, determination,
随机应变并鼓起勇气
resourcefulness and courage
在世界的屋脊
it is possible to make a life here
同样可以打造人生
at the roof of the world.
人类星球
镜头背后的故事
《人类星球》山区摄制组
When the Human Planet mountains
在拍摄蒙古鹰猎人时
team filmed the Mongolian eagle hunters,
在雪原上寻找狐狸
their search for a fox
就好比是海底捞针
was like finding a needle in a haystack.
在广阔的蒙古平原上
Keeping up with the hunters
要跟上猎人的步伐
also proved near impossible
更是难上加难
in the vast Mongolian landscape.
蒙古  阿尔泰山脉
北纬48°58′01″  东经89°58′01″
摄制组要跟拍塞劳和他的儿子贝瑞克
The team are here to film Sailau and his son Berik
带着猎鹰巴拉潘出猎的情景
hunting with their eagle, Balapan.
摄影师基思・帕特里奇
Cameraman Keith Partridge
上一次见到贝瑞克和他的小鹰
last met Berik
还是在六月份
in June with his newborn chick.
现在已是十一月份  天气很冷
It's now November and bitterly cold
是打猎的理想时节
an ideal time for hunting,
这时  狼  狐狸和兔子
when wolves, foxes and rabbits
都换上了厚厚的皮毛
all have thick winter coats.
与野生动物不同
Unlike the wildlife,
老式俄罗斯卡车并不适合天寒地冻的环境
the old Russian trucks are not well adapted to the cold
所以司机们想出了一个聪明的办法
so the drivers devise a novel solution.
凯斯选择了另一种交通工具
Keith opts for a different ride.
事实上
The fact is
我从未在黑泽海滩[英国的游乐场所]骑过驴
that I haven't even ridden a donkey across Blackpool beach.
基思・帕特里奇
摄影师
但现在却要骑马
And we've now got to go up there
前往山顶
on one of these.
我的马儿有名字吗
Does my horse have a name?
蒙古的马都没有名字
没有名字吗
They don't have names?
我们就根据它们的毛色叫名字
蒙古人光是形容马的毛色
The Mongolians have more than 300 words
阿吉・玛卡斯姆
剧务
就有三百多个词
just to describe the horse colours.
要让马走起来
You know that to make it go,
你得轻轻踢它的肚子  然后喊"驾"
you slightly kick and you should say, "Shu!"
好的  我们跟着阿吉好吗
OK, shall we follow Agii?
谢啦
Thank you.
就是这样
That's it.
终于  凯斯找到了窍门  顺利前行
Eventually, Keith finds the gears and off he goes.
三小时之后  卡车终于赶上来了
After three hours, the trucks catch up,
凯斯无比高兴能够离开马背了
and Keith's only too happy to leave his horse behind.
他觉得怎么样
What does he think?
骑得很好  马更棒一些
你这人除了鼻子之外都挺不错的
我的鼻子吗
Except my nose?
是太大了吗
Is it too big?
没错
鼻子上会生冻疮的
你看  这样就不会冻了
There you go, no frostbite!
凯斯着手去测试小型鹰载摄像头
Keith heads off to test a small "Eagle-cam",
塞劳还特制了安全带
for which Sailau has made a harness.
别的摄像头可能图画效果更好一些
There are cameras that might give us a better picture quality
但是要比这个大得多
but they're much bigger
所以我们一直在可行性和图画质量
so we're playing this trade-off game all the time
之间权衡
between practicalities and quality.
不管怎样  我们看看这个效果如何
Anyway, we'll see how it goes.
看起来  塞劳的鹰
Sailau's eagle seems
背着那个摄像头飞得很欢
to fly quite happily with the eagle-cam on her back.
受第一次试验的鼓舞
Encouraged by the first test,
剧组换上了一个重一些且更清晰的摄像头
they use a heavier high-definition camera.
如果这个能成功就太棒了
This will be amazing if this works.
我们不知道它能不能承受得住这个重量
We don't even know if the bird will take the weight.
好比飞机超载了
We might have overloaded the plane, so to speak.
鹰翱翔的姿态很优美
The eagle flies beautifully.
凯斯和剧组人员回到基地
Keith and the team head back to base,
和导演尼克・布朗一起查看拍摄效果
joining director Nic Brown to view the results.
真是个紧张时刻
It's a very tense moment.
当地人也想看看俯视效果
The locals join in for a bird's-eye view.
他们从未从这种角度看过自己的鹰
They've never seen their eagles quite like this before.
-眼罩拿掉了  -没错
- The hood's off! - Hood's off.
开始了
Off we go.
-真小啊  上帝  真有意思  -看它的头
- How small, my God. Really wild! - Look at his head!
看它头部周围的雪堆
Look at that banking round with the head.
太有趣了  是吧
That's pretty wicked, isn't it?
第二天
The next day,
剧组跟着贝瑞克和
the crew follow Berik and
他的小鹰第一次出门狩猎
his young eagle on their first fox hunt.
狩猎者紧随驱逐者
The hunters shadow sweepers-
就是负责把狐狸赶到空旷地面的人们
men who flush the foxes out into the open.
剧组必须不停从一个山头移到另一个山头
The team must constantly move from peak to peak
为了给鹰一个最佳视野
to give the eagles the best chance of seeing a fox.
塞劳认为狐狸应该就藏在
Sailau thinks that the fox might be hiding
这些电话线后面的小山头里
over these small mounds just behind these telegraph lines.
他想去其中一个山头等等看
He would like to go to one of those hills and wait there.
也就是说我们得赶去那边
It seems to make sense that we've got to head there.
你最好快点  伙计  他已经出发了
Well, you'd better be fast, mate, cos he's just gone.
他去那了
There he goes.
摄影组迅速打包  紧追猎人的步伐
After packing up quickly, the film crew race after the hunters.
正当凯斯开始摄影时
But as soon as Keith starts filming,
计划似乎又被打破了
the plans seem to change yet again.
塞劳现在又转移了  所以  我们也得转移
Sailau's now moved off again so, er, time to go.
我们才在这里待了两分钟
We've only been here for two minutes.
这就定下了今天的基调
This set the pattern of the day.
塞劳和贝瑞克从一个山头赶往另一个山头
As Sailau and Berik move from peak to peak,
剧组也一样  马不停蹄
so do the team, constantly
在高海拔处缺氧的状态下玩你追我赶游戏
playing catch-up in the thin, high-altitude air.
最后  精疲力尽之时  他们遇到一个新问题
Finally, near exhaustion, they face a new problem.
塞劳在哪儿
Where is Sailau?
他们呼叫导演
They call the director.
尼克  尼克  这是凯斯  听得见吗  完毕
Nic, Nic. This is Keith, do you read? Over.
收到  你们进展如何
'Hi, yeah, how are you?'
今天已经跑了三个山头了
We're on our third mountain
但是任务还没有完成
range of the day so far and still no luck.
你们现在在哪座山  完毕
'Which mountain range are you on now? Over.'
我们要是知道就好了
If only we knew!
我们身后的山顶峰没有积雪
Behind us are the really big peaks with no snow on.
说实话  这里一片荒芜
The terrain here is pretty wild, actually,
如果要藏什么东西
and if anything's going to be lurking about,
我觉得就这附近最好了
I think I'd want to hide around here somewhere.
电线杆前面有东西  是狗吗
Something's in front of that telegraph pole. Is that a dog?
我们装上镜头看看
Let's get the lens on it.
不是狼  是头牛
It's not a wolf, it's a cow!
祖宾・萨罗
录音师
我又没说是狼  我只说是个活物
I never said it was a wolf, I said it was moving.
那可没错
That is very true!
今天在爬第三个山头时
Do I get the sense that delirium
我怎么感觉有些发晕呢
is beginning to set in on the third mountain range of the day?
吃点儿巧克力棒吗
Would you like some chocolate bars?
阿吉  每当我们快晕过去的时候...
Agii, every day, just at the point where we are about to faint...
你咬咬看
You bust your teeth on them!
阿吉  我想说
I could ask you, Agii,
你就不能把它们放在稍稍暖一点的地方吗
if you could keep them somewhere slightly warmer!
他们又出发了
They set off yet again.
凯斯和剧组
Keith and the team are
开始对摄制狩猎情景绝望了
beginning to wonder if they'll ever film a hunt.
然后  好消息来了
But then, good news.
我们看见了一只狐狸
We have seen a fox.
沿着那个雪坡迅速逃窜
It scarpered really fast down that snowy slope.
他俩就在这附近
The guys are over there at the moment,
等着它停下来
trying to see where it's hunkered down.
你能轻松地在雪中看到它们
Once they're out on the snow, you can see them pretty easily
因为那是个小黑点  拼命逃窜
cos it's a little black dot, scarpering like hell.
但是  你看看这地方
But, um, apart from that, you see this place.
非常广阔
It's utterly vast.
捕猎就像海底捞针一样困难
It's like trying to find a needle in a haystack.
突然  前面山谷传来了喊声  狩猎开始了
Suddenly, there's a call from the valley and the hunt is on.
请不要挡住镜头
Everybody clear the front of frame, please.
开始
Now!
这狐狸逃得真是快
I think the fox has made a hasty escape.
巴拉潘和剧组人员在第一次捕猎中
Both Balapan and the crew
都积攒了宝贵经验
have learned a lot on their first hunt.
剧组仍需拍摄一组成功狩猎的画面
Still...the team have yet to film a successful hunt.
数天过去  一无所获
After several frustrating days,
压力越来越大
the pressure to deliver is intense.
快没时间了  但效果都不是很好
We're fast running out of time, it hasn't been looking very good.
正当剧组人员准备投降时
Just when the crew are resigned to failure,
他们听到了喊声
a call is heard.
儿子  那有只狐狸
凯斯深知这是他和巴拉潘成功的大好机会
Keith knows this is his and Balapan's big chance to succeed.
巴拉潘成功了
The bird got it!
当所有的呐喊声沉寂之后
When all those whoops go off,
仅仅数秒之内  拍摄进度
things just go from nought to a million miles
从颗粒无收变成了一日千里
an hour in two or three seconds.
做这种事情的时候心跳会加速
Your heart races when you are doing this sort of stuff,
你需要用一种积极的方式去回应
and you just have to respond in a kind of a positive way.
努力尝试
You know, just try and stay
全身心投入到工作中去
totally focused on what you are here to do.
当肾上腺素分泌时  很容易就分神了
When that adrenaline kicks in, it's easy to get distracted,
但你得想想
but you have to just think,
好了  现在是我上场的时候了
"Right, now is the time I've got to up my game,
沉下心来认真工作  完成拍摄任务
knuckle down and focus on getting the shot and making it work."
并且试图与你的工作伙伴
And also trying to build some form of relationship
建立良好的合作关系
with the people that you are working with as well.
只有这样他们才能信任我们
So that they trust us
敞开双臂欢迎我们走进他们真实的生活
and welcome us into what's quite an intimate part of their lives.